A Finding Aid to the Sidney Laufman Papers, 1916-1983, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Sidney Laufman papers
1916-1983
Archives of American Art
Laufman, Sidney, 1891-
AAA.laufsidn
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of Sidney Laufman measure 1.0 linear feet and date from 1916 to 1983. The papers document Laufman's career as a landscape painter through awards, biographical outlines, and interviews; correspondence with family, friends, and art organizations; notebooks, notes, and other writings; receipts, sales records, and other personal business records; clippings, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material; and photographs of Laufman and his family and photographs of artwork.
Biographical / Historical
Sidney Laufman (1891-1985) was a landscape painter. He studied at the Cleveland School of Art, the School of The Art Institute of Chicago, and under Robert Henri at the Art Students League of New York. After World War I, he and his wife settled in Paris where he worked for thirteen years before returning to the United States. He was active in the Federal Emergency Relief Administration in Florida and the WPA in New York. He also taught at the Art Students League in 1938.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1916-1980 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, ca. 1922-1983 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, 1920-1955 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1923-1975 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1927-1982 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 6: Photographic Material, 1935-1966 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Scope and Contents
The papers of Sidney Laufman measure 1.0 linear feet and date from 1916 to 1983. The papers document Laufman's career as a landscape painter through awards, biographical outlines, interviews, and other biographical material; correspondence with family,friends, and art organizations; notebooks, notes, and other writings; receipts, sales records, and other personal business records; clippings, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material; and photographs of Laufman and his family and photographs of artwork.
Biographical material includes awards and citiations, a biographical outline, an audio reel oral history interview with Laufman, and small oil paintings. Correspondence includes letters from Louis Bouche, Eliot Clark, Ralph Fabri, Leon Kroll, Ethel Magafan, Meyer Schapiro, and art dealers. Writings include typescripts of lectures and writings; five notebooks relating to his techniques, materials, and style, lists of works, and business notes, 1942 to 1952; a journal and a typescript of the journal kept by his wife Beatrice, ca. 1938-1955. Business records include receipts, sales records, and dealings with East End Gallery, Living American Art, and Milch Galleries. Printed material includes newpaper clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, and programs for the Third Woodstock Art Conference. Photographic material consists of personal photographs of Laufman with family and friends and photographs of Laufman's artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Sidney Laufman papers were donated to the archives between 1983-1984 by Sidney Laufman.
Related Materials
Syracuse University also holds a portion of the Sidney Laufman papers.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Sidney Laufman conducted by Joseph Trovato, January 29, 1965.
Interviews; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- France -- Paris; Laufman, Beatrice R., -1980
- Biographical Material, 1916-1980; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes awards and citiations, a biographical outline, an audio reel oral history interview with Laufman, and small oil paintings.
  - Awards, 1951-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Data, 1916-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oral History Interview, 1967 September 7; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Paintings by Beatrice Laufman, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, circa 1922-1983; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence includes letters from Louis Bouche, Eliot Clark, Ralph Fabri, Leon Kroll, Ethel Magafan, Meyer Schapiro, and art dealers.
  - Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, circa 1922-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, circa 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sidney Laufman Exhibition Party, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Writings, 1920-1955; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include typescripts of lectures and writings; five notebooks relating to his techniques, materials, and style, lists of works, and business notes, 1942 to 1952; a journal and a typescript of the journal kept by his wife Beatrice, ca. 1938-1955.
  - Notebooks, 1920-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Notes and Writings, 1946-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Beatrice Laufman's Journal, 1939-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Transcript of Beatrice Laufman Journal, 1938-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-27)
  - Beatrice Laufman, Letter to "Fan", 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
  - Transcript of Beatrice Laufman's Letter to "Fan", 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Personal Business Records, 1923-1975; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Business records include receipts, sales records, and dealings with East End Gallery, Living American Art, and Milch Galleries.
  - East End Gallery, Forum Gallery, 1959-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Living American Art, 1936-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Milch Galleries, circa 1934-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Mrs. Albert Sterner, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sales Records, 1934-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Receipts and Miscellaneous, 1933-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Printed Material, 1927-1982; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Printed material includes newpaper clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, and programs for the Third Woodstock Art Conference.
  - Clippings, 1927-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1927-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Exhibition Invitations, 1953-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Press Releases, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Third Woodstock Conference, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Photographic Material, 1935-1966; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Photographic material consists of personal photographs of Laufman with family and friends and photographs of Laufman's artwork.
  - Personal, 1935-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Artwork, circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48-52)